<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC 
   "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
   "docbook/docbookx.dtd">
<refentry id='gpsflash.1'>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>gpsflash</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class='date'>15 Jul 2005</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>
<refnamediv id='name'>
<refname>gpsflash</refname>
<refpurpose>2-stage firmware loader for GPS chipsets</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<refsynopsisdiv id='synopsis'>

<cmdsynopsis>
  <command>gpsflash</command>  
      <arg choice='opt'>-n</arg>
      <arg choice='opt'>-l <replaceable>loader-file</replaceable></arg>
      <arg choice='plain'>-f <replaceable>firmware-file</replaceable></arg>
      <arg choice='req'><replaceable>tty</replaceable></arg>
</cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsect1 id='description'><title>DESCRIPTION</title>

<para>This program is a firmware loader for GPSes connected to your
host computer via serial or USB port.  Presently it supports only SiRF
GPSes.  Other GPSes may be supported in the future if the vendors
cooperate.</para>

<para>For operation, this program requires a flashloader binary (found
by default in a file named <filename>dlgsp2.bin</filename>) and a
firmware image. This program first ships a command that tells the GPS 
a flashloader image will follow, then gives the GPS time to reboot into the
flashloader. The flashloader then accepts S-records from the serial
or USB port until it sees a termination record, at which point it
writes the new firmware into the GPS's non-volatile memory
and reboots the chip into the new firmware.</para>

<para>There is one required argument, specifying the serial device to
which the GPS is connected.</para>

<para>The -l option specifies the flashloader binary.  The -f option
specifies the firmware image file, and is required unless you
are just probing the GPS (-n option).</para>

<para>If the -n option is specified, the program will probe the
GPS to try to determine its type and whether the upload is
compatible, but not actually perform the upload. When this option
is specified, the -f option is not required.</para>

<para>You will need to obtain your own copy of
<filename>dlgsp2.bin</filename> and your own firmware image.  The GPSD
project does not yet have permission to distribute these files, so
don't ask us for copies.</para>

<para>Depending on your GPS type, this program may or may not attempt
to check that the flashloader or firmware image is compatible with
your GPS; in some cases no check is possible.  <emphasis
role='strong'>EXPERIMENT AT YOUR OWN RISK.</emphasis>
</para>

<para>This program will only work with firmware images in S-record
format, which is the form SiRF normally distributes them in.  If you
get a binary firmware image from somewhere, you can use
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>objdump</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
from the GNU binutils to convert it to S-records.</para>

<para>Realize that we are not kidding around when we say that this
could very well break your receiver permanently, and if it does, it's
no one's fault but your own. For this program to flash your GPS, you must set
an environment variable called I_READ_THE_WARNING with the value "why
oh why didn't i take the blue pill".</para>

<para>This program emits progress messages to standard output.</para>

<para>The GPS will be reset to 4800bps NMEA after flash.</para>

</refsect1>
<refsect1 id='bugs'><title>BUGS AND LIMITAIONS</title>

<warning><para>THIS PROGRAM CAN DESTROY YOUR GPS.  A botched firmware upload
will turn it into a paperweight.  USE AT YOUR OWN RISK.  Maintainers
are not responsible for direct or incidental damages.  YOU HAVE BEEN
WARNED.</para></warning>

</refsect1>
<refsect1 id='see_also'><title>SEE ALSO</title>
<para>
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>gpsd</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>gps</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>libgps</refentrytitle><manvolnum>3</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>libgpsd</refentrytitle><manvolnum>3</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>srec</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry>.
</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='maintainer'><title>AUTHOR</title> 

<para>Chris Kuethe <email>chris.kuethe@gmail.com</email>.  There is a
project page for <application>gpsd</application> <ulink
url="http://gpsd.berlios.de/">here</ulink>.</para>

</refsect1>

</refentry>
