	<section id="install-linux">
		<title>
			Toolkit Installation on Linux
			</title>
		<para>
			The Linux version of the toolkit must be compiled from source code. The only requirement is the standard <application>GNU/Linux</application> toolchain consisting of <application>make</application>, <application>gcc</application> and <application>ld</application>. These are included with most <application>Linux</application> distributions but may require installation. On <productname>Debian</productname> based distributions, such as <productname>Ubuntu</productname>, they may be installed using <application>apt-get</application>. On <productname>RedHat</productname> distributions, such as <productname>Fedora</productname>, they may be installed using <application>rpm</application>. On <productname>SuSE</productname> based distributions, they may be installed using <application>YaST2</application>.
			</para>
		<section>
			<title>
				Toolkit Installation on GNU/<productname>Linux</productname>
				</title>
			<example>
				<title>
					Toolkit Installation on GNU/<productname>Linux</productname>
					</title>
<screen>
# cp plc-utils-1.2.1.tar.gz /home/mydir
# cd /home/mydir
# tar -vzxf plc-utils-1.2.1.tar.gz
# cd plc-utils-1.2.1
# make
# make install
# make manuals
</screen>
				</example>
			<para> 
				Decompress the archive and extract the contents with the <application>tar</application> utility. This will create a folder having the same basename as the archive such that one version will not over-write another. Consult the <application>tar</application> man page on your system for detailed instructions. Change directory to the appropriate folder.
				</para>
			<para>
				The main package folder contains a recursive <filename>Makefile</filename> that will compile and install all toolkit programs. If you do not want to compile and install all programs then change directory to the appropriate folder and run <application>make</application> from there. To compile binary files, type <userinput>make</userinput>. To install binary files, type <userinput>make install</userinput>. To install man pages, type <userinput>make manuals</userinput>. The package does not automatically install examples, scripts, applets or man pages. 
				</para>
			<para>
				We recommend that you <command>login</command> as <constant>root</constant> user before installing the toolkit; otherwise, you will be prompted for the <constant>root</constant> password as each program or component is installed. 
				</para>
			<para>
				Programs are installed in folder <filename>/usr/local/bin</filename> and man pages are installed in folders <filename>/usr/share/man/man1</filename>. If these folders are not correct for your system, or if you want to install in other folders, then edit the folder names defined in the <link linkend="software-cross-compile">make.def</link> file found in main toolkit folder or over-ride these definitions in subordinate makefiles.
				</para>
			</section>
		<section>
			<title>
				Toolkit Documentation on GNU/Linux
				</title>
			<para>
				Toolkit web pages are not automatically installed. To access toolkit documentation, point your browser to <ulink url="index.html">docbook/index.html</ulink> and add the page to the browser bookmark or favorites list. If you are interested in how the toolkit has been implemented then do the same for page <ulink url="toolkit.html">docbook/toolkit.html</ulink>. 				</para>
			<para>
				The method described above is only recommended if you do not plan to move or remove toolkit folders. Otherwise, you can merely copy the entire contents of the toolkit <filename>docbook</filename> folder to another folder of your choice and point your browser to the new file locations.
				</para>
<screen>
cp -rv docbook/* /home/mydir/toolkit
</screen>
			</section>
		<section>
			<title>
				Toolkit Removal on GNU/<productname>Linux</productname>
				</title>		
			<para>
				To uninstall installed programs and man pages on Linux, change to the main toolkit folder and type <userinput>make uninstall</userinput>.
				</para>
			<example>
				<title>
					Toolkit Removal on GNU/<productname>Linux</productname>
					</title>
<screen>
# cd /home/mydir/plc-utils-1.2.1
make uninstall
</screen>
				</example>
			</section>
		</section>
