This is 80. The missing man should
be considered extremely dangerous..
81-20, can you hear me? Come in.
Eight, one, two, zero.
Can you hear me? Come in.
News-flash. A policeman was killed
and another was badly injured-
- In a violent assault on County Road 46
at six o'clock in the afternoon.
The perpetrator disappeared in the police car.
According to the police there's
not yet a description of the offender-
- But the incident has been linked
with events in Gosseberga-
- Where the wanted Lisbeth Salander
was arrested after the shooting incident.
She's being treated at Sahlgrenska Hospital
and her condition is critical.
The police are expected to convene
for a press conference later today.
We've removed a bullet from her head.
It's a serious injury.
And she has gunshot wounds
in the left hip and right shoulder.
- Can she make it?
- She's stable now.
Without complications
it should work.
- May I visit her?
- Not now.
I'm a close friend.
You can wait, but I promise nothing.
I'm coming.
- Is Lisbeth Salander innocent?
- I don't know.
Read it. He commited serious
legal assaults against Salander.
Everything's documented here.
It's a police report from '93.
It's classified.
Where did you get that?
- Mike Blomkvist from Millennium.
- Where did he get it from?
That you may have to ask him.
Hello.
Can you open your eyes?
My name is Anders Jonasson.
I'm a doctor here.
You're in Sahlgrenska
Hospital in Gothenburg.
Can you count to ten?
One, two, three, four...
That is good.
Thanks. Hello.
- Do we have any names?
- Yes, Holm and Jonasson.
- Oh, shit.
- You can see her now. Three minutes.
You have to get through this, Lisbeth.
I would like to report a crime.
My daughter tried to murder me.
We will get to that, but first
tell us about Ronald Niedermann.
We believe he murdered a police officer
and wounded another in the afternoon.
I don't know what he's doing.
But I do know, however,-
- that my daughter tried
to kill me tonight.
Ronald Niedermann is wanted.
Do you know where he could be?
No. But between us ...
I'm getting a little afraid of him.
I'm just
an old injured man.
Disabled.
- We know who you are.
- We've read your SAPO file.
We want to hear from you
on the three Stockholm murders of-
journalist Dag Svensson
and his girlfriend Mia Bergman.
And the sollicitor Nils Bjurman.
That I know nothing about.
Nothing.
Damn it. Next time we hear from
him, we must be better prepared
I'm going to Gosseberga now.
Some colleagues promised to pick me up.
- See you.
- Yeah, see you.
- Hi.
- Hi. Have you met Lisbeth Salander?
- They said she was sedated.
- She is.
Have you met Zalachenko?
What did he say?
- What happens now?
- I must speak with the doctors.
Then take the train to Stockholm.
You can ride with me. I have a car.
If you want to.
- Dr Jonasson will be here shortly.
- Thanks.
I intend to write the story about Lisbeth
and publish it in Millennium.
I intend to write it all.
The Security Service and a psychiatrist
got her locked in a madhouse.
- There will be some trouble.
- Yes, that's for sure.
Until you see
that Niedermann is involved.
Proof of that is pretty thin yet.
And he's not the type to confess.
I need someone on the inside
that I can trust.
I need to know what happens
regarding the indictment against Lisbeth.
It sounds like a good way
to get fired.
Place her in seven and prepare her,
I'll look at it later.
I was wondering when you would show up.
We've discussed
how we'll help you.
But to develop a strategy
we need to hear your version, too.
And how should
the strategy look?
We'll find out together.
But it'll probably be hard to
avoid a short prison sentence.
Ah. Is that so?
We'll assist with a lawyer
and all that's needed.
But you must cooperate
and give us some guarantees.
Niedermann.
Niedermann is the culprit!
It was he who shot Lisbeth.
There are currently serious allegations against you.
It'll be hard to get around them.
That's your problem.
If you don't solve it-
- I'll contact the media.
I have names,
dates, events ... everything.
I can crush you, completely.
I'm a survivor.
You ought to know that by now.
- Zalachenko, you don't understand ...
- It's you who doesn't understand!
This conversation is over.
News-flash.
After the Gosseberga police murder-
- the search for
the offender has intensified.
The police have identified him as
35-year-old Ronald Niedermann.
He's blond, short hair,
205 cm tall, and powerfully built.
He's armed and considered
extremely dangerous by the police.
No, no, no!
Hello, Lisbeth.
How are you?
Do you remember me?
Anders Jonasson's my name.
It's understandable if you're tired.
You had a bullet wound in the head.
We managed to remove the bullet.
It hasn't damaged any vital parts,
As far as we can see.
You also had gunshot wounds
in the right shoulder and left hip.
But it seems that they will heal fine.
Can it give me brain damage?
That's complex and sometimes difficult to see,
but you shouldn't worry.
The police wanted to talk to you.
But I said no,
because of your condition.
I'm sure they'll return,
but I won't let them come yet.
How is Zalachenko?
You mean Karl Axel Bodin?
He's down the corridor.
Severly beaten, but he's patched
and his condition is stable.
Damn.
My Text is between 40 and 50 pages.
I want to have parts of the Björck
investigation by fax.
To make it stronger, better looking.
- What kind of photos do we have?
- Not much.
We can get pictures of Gunnar Björck,
Teleborian and Zalachenko.
- Some people from St. Stephen's Hospital.
- Yes, and Lisbeth.
- It sounds like at least 75 pages.
- There may be more. It'll be good.
- Can we get more names?
- No, we must focus on what we have.
We can hope that the publication
will shed some light on this.
That one thing leads to another, and so on.
Now let's get to work.
How are you, anyway?
You look quite worn out.
- I'm completely drained.
- You want to talk?
No, not now. I gotta go home and sleep.
Then I should do it.
Go home and sleep now. Okay?
Her name is Lisbeth Salander.
Sweden has come to know her through
press conferences and headlines.
She is 27 years old.
A meter and a half in height.
She's been described as psychopathic,
murderess, and a lesbian satanist.
We reveal how government officials
conspired against her-
- To protect a pathologically
deranged killer.
Alexander Zalachenko is a renegade
GRU agent from the Soviet Union.
In Sweden, he is guilty
of serious crimes:
Arms trading, drug dealing,
and sex trafficking.
Alexander Zalachenko is
Lisbeth Salander's father.
Mr Bodin. Come, let's go back.
This isn't your room.
This way.
Salander struck again.
MURDERER HUNTED THROUGHOUT SWEDEN
- There you go, keep it.
- Thanks.
- I'm looking for Fredrik Clinton.
- Who may I say is calling?
- An old colleague of his.
- Father's resting, but come inside.
Zalachenko does what's best
for him regardless of consequences.
That's my assessment, too.
If he starts talking,
he must have proof.
The evidence is only available
in the archive, and he can't get in.
No, he can't.
But we can't risk that
he starts talking.
We need to silence him
at any cost.
On that we agree.
As usual.
But you can see how I am.
Fredrik, we need you.
One last time.
I can't.
I spend five hours-
- Every other day at the hospital
on the dialysis machine,
I will die soon.
I can't get a new kidney.
That's it, my friend.
- Thanks honey.
- They're freshly baked.
I didn't know
you had a daughter.
No.
We don't know too much
about each other's private lives.
Despite the fact that we've
worked together for...
yes, more than 35 years.
Lisbeth Salander, then?
The indictment's already started.
What do we do with her?
The prosecutor wants Lisbeth arrested
for the attempted murder of Zalachenko.
But the trial will be about equally important
things as the assassination attempt.
What happened in Gosseberga
is the result of a long story.
It's about violence, exploitation
of Lisbeth and her mother.
Here you have strong evidence
to build your defense on.
- This is classified.
- Don't worry about it.
You got it from a journalist
who didn't say where it came from.
THE PRIME MINISTER
DANGER
MURDER
OBSERVER
KING OF SWEDEN
Archbishop
PRIME MINISTER
SJ's X2000 No. 429 from Stockholm
has arrived on track number 6.
I don't need a lawyer.
You'll be charged with
the attempted murder of your dad.
Micke thinks they'll try to get you
in the mental hospital again-
- So yes, you need a lawyer.
But you can choose another.
Unless you want the court to
appoint a public defender.
Does your silence mean
I should leave?
It's your choice.
Do you have a cigarette?
- Do you have a nicotine patch?
- Yes, one moment.
Hi, I'm in Room Three,
Will the stretcher come soon?
I got this from Micke.
I think you know what it contains?
The two of us need to talk
a lot with each other.
So I want you to be completely
honest with me.
Micke's told me most of it,
but some things he says that-
- You must decide
if you want to tell.
I assume you know
what he thinks.
There's something about computers
and a DVD.
After everything we've done for you
through the years-
- Then you threaten us.
It's quite rude.
I'm a survivor.
I do what I must to survive.
No, you do it because you're an evil
and throughly rotten man without honor.
Without morality.
I came here
to give you our answer.
We won't help you this time, you bastard.
You have no choice.
Do you not understand that?
Life has taught me
that there's always a choice.
Idiots.
- I'll crush you.
- You won't do anything.
No, lay down!
Sorry! I'll go and see what happened.
Out!
He has a gun!
Quick!
Wait, I'm coming.
Hold me tight.
Hold on to me.
No ...
We monitor airports and ferry berths
and we should continue to do so.
What are the chances that Niedermann's
left the country?
I think he's in Sweden.
But he's hunted throughout Europe.
He won't go anywhere.
- No girlfriends?
- He's lived as a hermit.
He's only had contact with
Zalachenko, who lied to him.
But he listened to Zalachenko anyway.
You've read the report...
Gunnar Björck's.
I've browsed through it.
Maybe he thinks with Zalachenko
he's protected
That's why he didn't say anything.
Yeah, maybe so.
But we must keep him out of this.
To be more precise, we need him.
The public prosecutor has withdrawn
the investigation, so it's moot.
What the hell are you saying?
Björck's investigation is useless
because it's classified.
Zalachenko was shot.
He's dead.
Someone came in Sahlgrenska
and shot him dead.
Why didn't the police
provide better protection?
Completely incomprehensible. You wouldn't
think things like that could happen here.
Going armed into a hospital
and killing a patient is incredible.
He pulled the door handle, but couldn't
open it. It was so unreal.
An old man with a gun.
Then I heard the shot,
when he shot himself.
Are you sure he tried
to get to Lisbeth?
Yes, it was awful!
I've never been so scared.
- Should I come down to you?
- No.
You don't need to come. I'll sleep
with my friend Vera Åkerlund in Kålltorp.
- The press conference is at 15:00 at the police station.
- I'll have to run.
- Take care of yourself now.
- Yep.
- We'll talk.
- OK. Bye.
Well... Fredrik?
What in the world...?
Come in, come.
We're trying to get information
about it now.
At what time was it?
Find out now.
What the hell?
- You've heard what happened?
- Zalachenko has been shot.
It seems Evert Gullberg
shot him.
It's chaos down there.
We haven't had any confirmation.
Then I can confirm it.
It was Evert who shot him.
To complete the plans.
- Should I get coffee or something?
- No, not now.
What the hell are you talking about?
What plans?
Gullberg had only a few months
left to live. He had liver cancer.
He chose to make a final,
last effort for us.
He went down with honors.
- You knew he would kill him?
- Of course.
His mission was
to silence Zalachenko.
And Salander too, that was the plan.
Are you equally as
insane as Gullberg?
Watch your mouth, Hallberg.
It was the right decision.
- We did what was necessary.
- Necessary? Decision?
You and Gullberg have no right
to decide anything!
Whatever happens, Zalachenko's
death can't be linked to us.
Not Evert Gullberg either.
Our task is to
make the decisions-
- That no one else dares to make.
Least of all, politicians.
It's that simple.
And one more thing ...
I've come back into service.
I lead the operational activities-
- Until this crisis is over.
The man who fired the lethal
shot and then took his own life-
- has been identified
as a 78-year-old pensioner.
He's worked as an
accountant and a tax lawyer.
- What was his name?
- We will not disclose that at this time.
Is there a connection
to Lisbeth Salander?
We can certainly reject any possible
connection to Lisbeth Salander.
This was a lonely perpetrator
who acted as he did-
- based on his own
paranoid imagination and ideas.
He's sent confused messages
to famous politicians and the media-
- In which there are death threats
to Karl Axel Bodin.
Why?
Security Services are investigating,
but he was probably mentally ill.
What does this have to do with
the case against Lisbeth Salander?
Currently nothing.
Karl Axel Bodin had given his testimony-
And we have forensic evidence
against Salander.
He tried to enter
Lisbeth Salander's room-
- But you don't see any
connection with Salander.
Why would he try
Getting into her room?
No comment. But we've strengthened
our monitoring of Sahlgrenska.
He claims that Bodin
was behind the Palmer murders-
And poisoned folks with chlorine.
Sick and sad.
How did he come in contact
with Zalachenko?
He shoots Zalachenko, goes
for Lisbeth, and it's a coincidence?
I don't know.
What if he knew
Karl Axel Bodin was Zalachenko-
And his daughter, Lisbeth.
A handful of people knew
Zalachenkos' identity. Not Gullberg.
But think again.
This is about something else, huh?
That we shouldn't exclude,
but everything shows-
- That there is a confused old
uncle from Gnesta who derailed.
The public prosecutor has withdrawn
Björcks' report.
Because the contents
are classified.
It figures.
Talking to you, Vera. Hello.
Hey!
Can I get my bag?
Give me the bag!
What the hell!
A guy on a moped snatched my bag.
What? How are you?
Are you okay?
Yeah, I'm good. But Björcks'
investigation was in that bag.
It's okay. I have a copy.
Annie, I'll call you.
- Annie.
- Yes
They've snatched my copy, too.
I went home to check.
- It's catastrophic.
- That's the least one can say.
It's the most powerful evidence for Millenniums' next issue.
The whole thing's collapsed.
No ... Shit, shit, shit!
- What do you think?
- I don't know.
- What can we do?
We don't have any evidence against Teleborian
and Björck. It's awful.
- Sonny? When did you get out?
- This morning.
- Magge too?
- No, he'll remain there for a while.
- Nice to see you. Do you know what happened?
- No idea.
The police did a raid
on the day you were arrested.
They found nothing. Then the blond bastard
came here looking for a place to hide.
You and Magges' buddy.
He's not my pal.
He's hunted throughout Sweden.
Therefore, he needed a hideout.
I sent him home to Viktor.
Damn ...
Sonny!
What the hell?
Jenny ... Jenny!
Jenny!
Jenny? It's me - Sonny.
Who was it?
Nieder ...
Niedermann.
Viktor, Viktor ...
Niedermann ...
He's gonna fucking die for this.
Decent of you to come here.
We don't meet so frequently nowadays.
No, we don't.
- Do you live out here permanently now?
- Yes.
You know about Evert Gullberg
at Sahlgrenska?
Yes.
I had no fucking clue.
- He and Clinton did it all.
- I thought Clinton was dead.
Not entirely.
Was he looking for Salander, too?
That's how it sounded on the news.
They should've both been silenced.
And the trial prevented.
That was the idea.
- Will he try for Salander again?
- No, it's probably too risky.
But Clinton could lock her
in the madhouse again.
It's been arranged before.
It feels like hell began when I gave
Nils Bjurmans' investigation.
There may be a link,
but you couldn't predict it.
No, but I think about it
all the time. It hurts me.
Don't wear it. Now the report
and it's copies are secure.
So at that point it's over.
What happens now?
I don't know.
But I think Clinton
is capable of anything.
Yes, Peter Teleborian.
This is Fred Clinton.
I assume based on Annika
that my phone's being tapped
We also assume-
- The editorial staff's phones
and your mobile is bugged.
So we shouldn't talk on the phones-
- But we will use these
with prepaid cards.
We use them only when we're talking about Zalachenko and proceedings with Lisbeth.
- Everything else we talk about normally.
- Is email secure?
No. We need to think about what we write
and encrypt it.
Don't you see? This would mean
that the entire editorial office was bugged.
No, because there's always someone.
Better to be on the safe side.
Any one of us can sleep over.
- We'll make a schedule until the trial.
- And get a sore back.
Björck's investigation was stolen in two places
on the same day. It's no coincidence.
Zalachenko's murdered neither.
Now they're trying to cover his tracks.
- The shooter at Sahlgrenska was a mental case.
- Or so they would have us believe.
But I don't think so anymore.
Then those who protected Zalachenko
started it. SAPO: then?
Yes, it could be SAPO:
but we don't know.
But they have great resources
and they're onto us.
The good news is that those who listen
to Mikael and Annika's phones-
- don't think we have access
to Björcks' report anymore.
And they must continue to believe that.
The indictment against Lisbeth Salander
isn't complicated.
Even if the plaintiff,
Alexander Zalachenko, is dead.
But if the truth about Zalachenko comes to light,
the trial may become more complicated.
It relates to human life and Swedish
relations with foreign nations-
- And the security police's
top-secret contacts.
I read the reports - well, mostly
as background material.
In the indictment against Lisbeth Salander
it has no great relevance.
And the Attorney has confiscated it.
But parts of it are useful.
Especially since Lisbeth Salander
has tried to kill her father before.
I'll see if you can get
access to that part.
Yes, perhaps it could be useful.
Then I'll make sure
you get it.
Who's your boss?
My orders come
from the very top.
This means that you can't
talk to anyone but me about this.
I'll be extremely discreet.
- It's Björck.
- Jan Bublanski, violence division.
- I propose a meeting.
- Oh, do you? Yeah.
I'm involved in an investigation
you can probably help me with.
The case of Zalachenko's murder.
You know a lot about him.
I left the service years ago.
I was thinking a friendly conversation
between colleagues...
- At home with you, maybe?
- I don't think so.
Of course I can also send
someone to bring you in.
All right. Come tomorrow, after 11.
How can he be so stupid
as to agree to a meeting?
What's he thinking?
Wasn't it Björck who gave
the Salander-investigation to Bjurman?
Yes, unfortunately.
- What's on the menu?
- Oh, yeah. Hamburger today.
- Go ahead.
- Thanks.
Lisbeth?
- Need Help?
- No thanks.
Enjoy your meal.
I have a suggestion.
I won't drive home.
I've made a reservation.
Will you sleep over?
I'm exhausted.
I hardly slept at the office.
So we'll just sleep.
This is the fourth time
I've seen this car here.
- Are you sure?
- Yes.
- Anders Jonasson?
Peter Teleborian.
I'm the senior consultant at
St. Stephen's psychiatric clinic in Uppsala.
I need to talk to you.
It's about one of your patients.
Lisbeth Salander.
- Yes?
- Well... Okay.
I've had her under my care
since she was twelve years old-
- And I have a very good insight into
her pyschological disorder.
- How does it look?
- Lisbeth is seriously mentally disturbed.
She has obvious delusions
with paranoid schizophrenic tendencies.
And like all sociopaths
She completely lacks empathy.
Simply put...
I perceive her as withdrawn,
but not as a paranoid sociopath.
She's extremely manipulative.
It's part of her disease.
She shows what she thinks you want to see.
Of course, I'm deeply
concerned for her mental condition.
I understand that.
I'll have to see her to assess
her condition before the trial.
Unfortunately, I can't help you.
I'm responsible for Lisbeth-
- and she's too weak to meet anyone
other than her lawyer.
I have the court's authorization
to have a meeting with her.
I had hoped to avoid being formal,
between colleagues, but I have to.
As her doctor, you should know that
it's my assessment that applies here-
- Regardless of what the court says.
So I must ask you to wait patiently
for my assessment to change.
Well.
I had hoped for a more
professional response.
Björck?
Hell.
Hello. Are you all right?
Can you look at it?
- How am I doing?
- You're definitely improving.
I'll make sure that you get help
To get started with rehabilitation.
- I don't need help.
- I think so. Don't scratch the crust.
And you should eat a little better.
You should do something about the food.
- Food?
- Get pizza or something.
I don't know if pizza's in the budget
of the County Council.
A Dr. Peter Teleborian
wanted to meet you.
He said that you had contact before.
He had to go with unfinished business.
Good.
It's been like this with us-
We have worked together
for decades-
- Without knowing each other privately.
We have worked a long time with Gunnar-
- I knew him as a strong
and reliable employee.
The fact that he chose to end
his life by his own hand-
- is hard to accept.
But it was his choice.
And that I respect.
Can we rule out
that the government's been aware of it?
They must've known that a Russian spy
defected to Sweden.
We had a conservative government in 1976,
when Zalachenko defected.
30 years and nothing has leaked out.
It wouldn't have been kept secret
if a lot of politicians knew about it.
They all write memoirs and biographies now.
It's the same with SAPO.
It'll be leaked sooner or later.
It may be a small secret group,
acting entirely on their own.
With significant resources
and influence.
If nobody's leaked about that group
in 30 years, where do we start digging?
The best lead we have
is Evert Gullberg.
We find something on him,
and perhaps it will lead further.
It must not take too much time though,
otherwise Millennium will be in trouble.
The magazine must go on sale,
simultaneously with the day the trial starts.
Suicide by hanging?
Gunnar Björck hanged himself
with his belt. That's it.
Who, apart from you, knows
that Bublanski contacted Björk?
Nobody - that I know of.
He knew a lot about Zalachenko
and Lisbeth. You've read the investigation.
Björck and Zalachenko are dead.
Gullberg tried to silence Lisbeth.
- Don't you think it fits together?
- We know nothing about Evert Gullberg.
- Conspiracy theories almost never work out.
- No, but it does for me.
They are trying to get to Lisbeth,
silence her, and manipulate the trial.
This isn't Belarus. You can't
manipulate trials in Sweden.
What are you talking about?
I don't know.
But the threat to Lisbeth increases.
She's exposed to a new legal
abuse or something far worse.
This one was for you.
Dr. Jonasson's responsibility for Lisbeth
Salander. It stands over my decision.
Yes, indeed,
but I had not anticipated-
- That he would begin to be
awkward and formal.
In addition, he refers
to Salander's lawyer-
And requires her approval.
Is this really correct?
Should a lawyer be allowed to impede
a psychiatric examination?
Of course not.
That's not like Jonasson.
But we have enough respect
for his medical assessment.
Salander gets better every day.
You may see her soon.
A study like this can take time.
Salander is a complicated case.
Goodbye.
These are from Björck's report,
as I promised you.
One more thing ...
There's been comments
from above-
- whether Jan Bublanski
is fit to lead this task.
Well?
- Will Faste take over the investigation?
- It's not his decision.
- Whose is it?
- Someone who believes in Faste.
I refuse to give it to that idiot.
That chauvinistic pig hates Salander.
That says enough about him, Sonja.
- I heard that we should split up.
- How long have you known?
Since late in the afternoon. Do you think
someone is conspiring with Ekstrom?
Can I get all the material
into my office as soon as possible?
- How's the Niedermann investigation?
- Things are going well enough.
I think the bastard's
left the country.
I don't like this.
Shit, I don't fucking like this.
Hello. We were at the hospital
the same night Lisbeth Salander came.
- I remember.
- I want to talk to you about somehing.
I won't disclose information
about Lisbeth Salander.
No, I want to give you information
about Lisbeth. Important information.
Such a conspiracy! Sorry,
but it sounds very unlikely.
I can very well understand what you think,
but I assure you - everything is true.
Everything can be documented, and
soon, I'll publish the whole story.
I'm also helping to build Lisbeth's defense
for her trial. That is why I'm here.
- I want to ask you one thing.
- What?
Lisbeth has secrets.
Private secrets, that she will
need in her defense.
To gain access to the evidence
against her, she needs this.
- The Prosecutor has forbidden her of communicating.
- So I ask you.
We have never faced
a more serious threat.
We need to close ranks
and defend ourselves.
Do you have anything else?
I just want to know
how Gunnar Björck died.
I knew him.
He would never have taken his own life.
There are things you never know.
I met Gunnar
Four weeks ago.
- There's nothing that suggests it.
- Did you meet him?
- Where?
- In his house in the country.
He just wanted to know what happened
when Gullberg shot Zalachenko.
- And there he was told?
- Yes.
Why shouldn't he know it?
And now I want to know how Gunnar died.
He hanged himself with his belt.
- Hey, how do you feel?
- Okay.
- Can I examine you?
- Yes.
Let's see...
- Does it hurt?
- No.
- What about your headaches?
- Okay.
- They disappear more and more.
- Good.
The policeman from Stockholm
called again.
He introduced himself as
the investigation leader.
He wants to come and question you.
Can you bend your head back a bit?
Not too much... He was quite annoyed
that we are so stuborn.
I can't keep them at bay with the excuse
of your medical condition much longer.
- You're getting well too quickly. Do you understand?
- Yes.
I said that you need
a couple more weeks.
After that you will be moved
to a detention center in Stockholm.
I saw the tattoo on your back.
It's quite large.
- Why have you done it?
- Why do you ask?
- Pure curiosity.
- Private reasons I will not mention.
All right. Sorry.
Oh, wow.
It must have hurt and taken time.
Yes, it both hurt
and took time.
Sorry.
Hello, Lisbeth. With this you can
tell your version of what happened.
Your autobiography.
Annika doesn't know that you have access
to this, and it must remain this way.
So this is the man in the black Saab?
Göran Mårtensson?
Coastal Hunter. Then the police academy.
Worked in the police from '91 to '96.
- Then he disappeared from external services.
- SAPO?
He is employed by the security police,
but is on loan to the counter-espionage.
They've never
heard of him.
- Do you think they're lying?
- No.
When someone tries to hide
and muddle what they're doing...
Unfortunately, our contact
knows no more than that.
What now then?
I can ask an old friend, but
then I'll be telling him everything.
- Who is it?
- He's working on the protection of the Constitution.
- He can go ahead with it.
- Is he reliable?
He's an old friend, Mikael.
- Yeah, okay. We'll be in touch.
- Yeah, all right.
To sum up what you said-
- several of the security police
officers connived-
- With a range of serious crimes
against a Swedish woman?
Had her daughter locked up
in a psychiatric hospital-
And gave a free pass to a defecting
Russian spy and his crimes?
Yes, it's a good summary.
In addition, they broke into
journalist Mikael Blomkvist's home-
And assaulted Annika Giannini,
Lisbeth Salander's lawyer.
The murder of Zalachenko
must now also be counted.
Constitutional protection must defend
democracy against internal threats,-
Usually nazis, anarchists...
But now you say that the threat comes
from our own organization?
Torsten, you may read it yourself.
See ya.
You are exempted from everything else.
Your only job is to investigate
the truth of this.
If even half of this is true,
we have a constitutional crisis to manage.
You have read the report, I'll find out
who Mårtensson works for.
Then you'll examine
Evert Gullbergs' background.
I have never heard of him,
but I may have access to the subject.
- You report only to me.
- Absolutely.
- Plague, are you there?
- Ciao, Wasp. How are you?
- I'll live. I need your help.
- Finally.
Peter Teleborian, psychiatrist.
I need access to his computer.
Send the content to Mikael
Blomkvist's hotmail address.
I'll need your help for
the trial. I'll pay 30,000.
- Do you have cash?
- Yes.
Mårtensson lives in Vällingby.
Lars Falusson is an old offender
who's now a locksmith.
A popular craft, apparently.
- Then they waited out Blomkvist?
- Yes, exactly.
- How long were they there?
- 40 Minutes.
- Mårtensson snooped around a lot.
- Did Blomkvist see them?
I didn't realize her presence
before I saw her there.
She filmed Mårtensson and Falusson.
- She works for Milton Security.
- Susanne Linder.
She was a cop until '98.
- Blomkvist hired Milton?
- It seems so.
The camera is between the lamp
and the roof in a recess.
We can fast forward if you don't
want to watch him tinker.
You can probably count on your apartment
being bugged now, Mikael.
We can remove it, if you want.
So revealing that you know
you're being watched.
No, let it be.
I can live in a different place.
It's okay to give the DVD to Annika;
but I'll write about the rape itself.
I've contacted Plague about Teleborian.
He will contact you
if he can find something.
We'll look for old ones. Judging from the color
it should be something from 1910.
That's right.
It doesn't look recent.
Don't you have a better picture
of Zalachenko?
You look tired. Don't you sleep
well when your husband is away?
Hello, hello. I have found
the connection to the government.
Guess who visited the Prime Minister
on October 5th, 1976?
Nobody? An Evert Gullberg and somebody
who called himself Hans von Rotting.
They were there three weeks after
Zalachenko defected.
- How did you find out?
- I checked the visitors book.
There was only one visit
on the 5th of October 1976.
Well done, Christer.
But we must prove that they were
there to inform him about Zalachenko.
- Were there any notes?
- No, just the name and date.
- How do we proceed?
- We drive to look at the State Secretaries.
- The two who worked there may know something.
- Do we have any names?
One is dead and the other is
a retired ambassador.
His name is Bengt Janeryd,
he lives outside Grisslehamn.
- We should have a chat with him.
- Good. I'll do it.
I know the material better than you
and I'm more dangerous to him.
- It's just what I say.
- Yeah, I heard it...
Address?
Yes.
You ...
Fucking well done.
Yes, Ekstrom.
Prosecutor Ekstrom just called.
- Can we take it later?
- No, this is serious.
Ekstrom was called anonymously,
someone wanted to talk about Zalachenko.
He wanted to talk about serious crimes being
committed during the preliminary investigation.
What crimes?
Ekstrom asked him to call back
in the afternoon and then phoned me.
The caller knows about the
investigation and Zalachenko.
If he calls again make sure
Ekstrom says yes to a meeting.
But explain that we're taking over now.
Emphasize it's a matter
of national security.
Choose an appropriate meeting place.
- Ekström.
- I called before about Zalachenko.
Of course, I'll hear
what you have to say over here.
- I'm busy now, but later in the evening?
- When?
- Nine o'clock would suit me.
- Nine o'clock's fine.
You must have understood that Gullberg
shot Zalachenko, right?
- You read the newspapers?
- Yeah.
- Why didn't you call the police?
- I was waiting for them to call me.
- It sounds a little convenient.
- I knew nothing about his daughter.
What she was subjected to is terrible.
But the prime minister didn't know about it.
Me neither.
You must convince both me
and Millennium readers about that.
I forbid you to use
my name in this context.
I haven't had anything
to do with it.
What I read here is news to me.
You have read some of the material
we'll publish. We have a lot more.
Everything can be proven.
I won't hang you out to dry,
but you have a responsibility and a debt.
Tell me what you know, and you will be a
confidential source. If not, I will expose you.
- I call that blackmail.
- Call it what you want.
Tell me and I promise
not to publish your name.
The Prime Minister informed me
about that meeting in October 1976.
He thought it was very uncomfortable.
It was the largest military
secret in Sweden that I know of.
So he was under a lot of pressure.
How many times did they meet
after the first meeting?
They didn't meet.
He didn't want to do it.
He made sure I was the intermediary
between him and the person-
- Who was in charge of Zalachenko.
I had to promise never to discuss
it with anybody and I've never done so.
The prime minister was in contact with Evert
Gullberg and Hans von Rottinger.
- Did you also meet with them?
- Yes.
There was a man: Clinton.
As the American president.
- Clinton?
- Yes.
How often did you meet?
About a dozen times during my time
as Secretary of State.
I didn't know anything.
Just that Zalachenko collaborated-
And that the information he gave
was invaluable.
Where did you meet?
Various places.
Often in apartments around town.
Who took over the connection
after the change of government?
I don't know.
- You handed over to no one?
- No.
You didn't report?
No, everything was, of course, top secret.
I hadn't even been allowed
to take notes during meetings.
So no subsequent government
had an idea-
- That there was a Soviet defector
in Sweden?
It sounds strange,
but it was so.
Hello, Mikael Blomkvist. Monica
Figuerola, Constitutional protection.
- Yeah?
- I would like to invite you to a chat.
It is a friendly invitation.
You risk nothing.
- Can I get my mail?
- Of course.
- And a pair of clean underpants?
- Absolutely.
Torsten Edklinth,
constitutional protection.
- Blomkvist.
- Please sit down.
You will understand
why we want to meet you.
So let's get right to it.
We have received confirmation of the
existence of a conspiracy-
- Within an exceptionally sensitive area
of state administration.
My meeting with the Prime Minister yesterday
resulted in the launch of a full investigation.
Which means ...?
A full investigation.
The result is given to the Attorney-General
who will decide whether prosecution should be instituted.
But we need time to identify
who is involved.
I understand very well.
Where do I fit in?
We want to know when you intend to publish.
If it's done before the investigation is concluded,
it could jeopardize the entire operation.
When can I
publish the proceedings?
It's obviously not something
we can determine.
It's totally up to you,
but we do ask that you cooperate.
What I can say is this ...
I am furious at the state,
Government, SAPO-
- And all the other fucking assholes
who put a 12-year-old girl in-
- a psychiatric ward without reason
and legally incapacitated her.
I myself am very upset about
what happened to Lisbeth Salander.
Those responsible will be punished.
But before that, we must identify
who's involved.
I would also like that.
But I also want Lisbeth Salander to be
acquitted and cleared with the authorities.
Then we or the government can't
intervene, you understand.
If I can gain insight into the investigation-
- I will tell what I intend to publish,
and when.
Information for information.
This can be solved fairly quickly.
We decide which employees
we recruit for the investigation.
We can hire Blomkvist
as an external consultant.
Evert Gullberg.
Do you have any more names?
Hans von Rotssinger, Fred Clinton.
One is dead, the other is retired.
- Both active in the group of '70-'80's.
- Group?
Can we give it a working title?
We can call it the Section.
Section? Sure.
How did you come up with that?
I have a good source.
- Can we keep hold of this place?
- I will sort it out.
What the hell?
Lisbeth tried several times
to tell the authorities-
- of Zalachenkos' assault
on her mother-
- But no one took the ten-year-old
girls' allegations seriously.
Only when she tried
to kill her father-
- To save her mother, did
society react.
But not by arresting and punishing
Alexander Zalachenko.
Instead, Lisbeth was punished.
at the age of twelve she was
forcibly taken away and locked up-
- At St. Stephen's Psychiatric
Hospital in Uppsala.
I tried to explain what happened
to Peter Teleborian-
- But he would not listen
and claimed that I fantasized.
I was strapped to the bed
as a punishment.
During the two years I was locked up -
- I was strapped to my bed
for 381 days.
Hello, Lisbeth.
How are you?
My assessment stands,
whatever the prosecutor decides.
We just do our job.
Want to argue about it.
What should we discuss?
That door should stay closed!
What the hell?
I was admitted.
You were not here when we arrived.
Get out of here.
The prosecutor decided it.
Lisbeth?
Look at me. What did he do?
It went too far. That won't
happen again. I promise you.
Right.
- Take care of his car.
- No problem.
We waited for over an hour.
Maybe he misunderstood the place.
- But he never showed up.
- Strange.
If he contacts you again,
you must notify me, immediately.
- Whose turn is it today?
- It's Malin's luck, huh?
Hello. How's it going?
- Sushi, is that okay?
- Not fish. Chicken teriyaki for me.
- Are you going to have lunch, Mike?
- No, I don't have time.
You sleep with the light on at night.
I see you. What am I?
All right. Erika, eight pieces?
May I change the battery with you?
Mine's flat.
Micke ... Look.
It's anonymous.
I think it's the same author as the last one.
- Have you had many?
- I got one last week.
- Why haven't you said anything?
- I didn't take it seriously.
Let's keep it between us,
we'll talk about that later.
- May I take it there?
- Take it.
- Will you have eight pieces?
- I'm not so hungry today.
I'll skip it.
I was strapped to the bed.
Peter Teleborian stood beside it.
He smelled of aftershave.
I hated his smell.
He wanted to make me happy
on my birthday.
I hated his voice.
I hated his hands.
It was the night I was 13 years old.
- Teleborians' opinion?
- A draft.
It needs to be processed,
but it looks good.
We've had an unexpected problem.
- Wadensjöö disappeared.
- disappeared?
Yes, his wife made a police report
in Bromma yesterday.
Last time she saw him was on friday morning.
Is there a risk that he defected
and told everything?
- Would Bertil do it?
- No, Bertil has always been loyal.
I think it feels
damn uncomfortable.
- What is it?
- We have a problem.
I checked Teleborians' hard disk
and mailbox and found nothing.
- Nothing?
- Nothing about you or the trial.
The only thing that can mean anything
are short emails from ...
Jonas on Hotmail.
"PSO 1 clear next week."
Dating from 20 September this year.
The second is equally brief:
"PSO 2 clear tomorrow."
PSO? Psychiatric opinion?
Or?
Yes, it could be.
- No files?
- No.
He hasn't sent anything
from his office computer.
He'll have a laptop
with mobile broadband.
- It could be difficult to access.
- But not impossible?
At the right time, everything is possible.
- I can keep track of his mailbox.
- Do it. But don't call anymore.
- SMS messages or email.
- Okay, bye.
Damn!
The trial begins on the 13th.
The magazine must be ready by then.
We need to go to press the week before.
- How will this be done?
- We must help each other.
You and Malin write about Teleborians
background and a little about St. Stephens.
Around 30 pages. Is this okay?
- Yes, it'll be okay.
- Good.
Yes ...
There's something else of importance.
I received two anonymous threats by mail-
- Last Week.
Thought you should know.
Threats?
Christ!
Who the hell sent them?
- Have you notified the police?
- I don't want the police here.
It's a serious threat to Erika.
We take it seriously. I don't want
to have the police at the office.
- So we'll just sit on it?
- That's not what I said.
- Let me fix it my way.
- How?
The police don't care about that sort of thing.
They don't give a shit!
Please, stop! Oh my God!
May we skip it? No harm was done.
Now we leave it.
30 pages?
- How about a cup of coffee?
- Yeah.
I have to hurry.
It's me.
Teleborian meets with Jonas
at four o'clock at the Center.
- What time is it?
- Half past three.
Damn!
- Hello. I need to take some blood.
- I have to go to the toilet first.
- Yes, it's Christer.
- I'm in the middle of the staircase.
Yes, I see you now.
I'm just below.
Now I can see Teleborian.
Christer, go ahead. I'll stop here.
All right.
You should see him soon.
Black jacket.
I see him now.
He's standing there, waiting.
- Watch him, not too close.
- No, I'm watching.
Someone is coming.
Must be Jonas.
Gray jacket, middle-aged.
I don't recognize him.
- Now they're leaving. Should I follow?
- Yes, follow them!
- They're going out towards Vasagatan.
- Follow them!
Mikael here. Teleborian has a meeting
with an agent of the Section.
- Okay. Where?
- At Vasagatan. Are you coming?
Okay. Yes, I'm on my way.
- Hi.
They're there.
- Mikael.
- They're leaving now.
Follow Teleborian.
We'll follow the other guy.
Monica here. I need information on
a car registration.
Teleborian has gone from the meeting
with Jonas Sandberg from the Section-
- To a meeting at Police Headquarters?
- With whom?
- Let's see ...
Jonas Sandberg was recruited
into counter-intelligence in 1998.
In 2001, he was transferred
to a secret location abroad.
He should be located at the Embassy in
Madrid, but they've never heard of him.
Same with Göran Mårtensson. Officially
moved to a place where he's not.
It can only go through
Secretary Albert Schenke.
The Section dwells in that house here.
A six-story,
23 flats condominium.
I've checked all the tenants
but there's nothing unusual.
Except the apartment at the very top.
Eleven rooms and a kitchen.
It's owned by the company Bellona.
The owners live abroad.
- Can we get a camera in?
- Do we have a warrant?
I'll get the warrant if you make
some tea.
Never mind... I'll make it.
- Hi.
- Am I disturbing you?
- hmm.
- I'll come back.
- I'm almost done.
I just wanted to warn you that
the police will come tomorrow.
All right.
I could postpone the transfer
a couple of days further, but...
- My colleagues would start to wonder.
- Then you shouldn't.
- Are you sure?
- Yes.
- You don't seem particularly worried.
- No.
I have a gift for you.
Why?
You have been one of my most
interesting patients in a long time.
If you're bored in jail, this is the
latest in DNA research.
- Your mobile ...?
- It's in the chocolate box.
Teleborian will write an
expert opinion.
He will report that you need treatment
at his psychiatric hospital.
The prosecutor requested this of him.
But we'll hire our own expert
who has his own opinion.
Lisbeth, this is for your own good.
I don't talk to any brain-bending doctors.
I've already said it.
Hope they fit.
You need to sort your attitude,
it could lose this case for us.
Lisbeth...
- Move!
- Lisbeth Salander ...
Do you have any comment?
Murder Suspect Lisbeth Salander
was transferred today by police escort-
- From Sahlgrenska in Göteborg
to the Kronobergs' jail in Stockholm.
According to prosecutor Richard Ekstrom
the trial is-
- Scheduled for November 6.
Lisbeth Salander is accused-
- Of the attempted murder of her father,
Alexander Zalachenko-
- Who was later brutally murdered
at Sahlgrenska Hospital.
There will be increased
security during the trial-
- Since some threats occurred
during the police investigation.
Here we have Georg Nyström.
Inspector, he's worked
in Security Service since 1983.
Since 1996 he's been an
independent investigator.
He makes internal controls on
cases that the Security Service completed.
Here is Jonas Sandberg again.
- Who is that?
- A neighbor, Karl Birgersson.
- Him I recognize ... Hallberg.
- Yes, Otto Hallberg.
He worked on anti-terrorism
15 years ago.
He resigned 9 years ago.
Has his own firm now.
Guess who he had lunch with today.
Your looking at it.
Secretary Albert Schenke
and Budget Director Atterbom.
That's how they get their money.
Everything is falling into place.
- I want a tag on them around the clock.
- So we need more people.
- What do you think about Jan Bublanski?
- Absolutely reliable.
- Got his hands full with Niedermann?
- No. He's probably left the country.
You need to come for questioning.
Yes, so we finally meet.
Ekstrom, prosecutor.
This initial meeting is more of a
conversation rather than an interrogation.
So we can try to get a handle
on this complicated story.
I assume that you don't
have anything against this.
The charges against you
are very serious.
But as the prosecutor, I should take into
account all mitigating circumstances.
It's important that you're aware
of it, for your own sake.
This is a simple question.
Answer yes or no.
When you went to Gosseberga
to meet your father-
- Were you already planning
to kill him?
I must ask the lawyer again to
get Salander to respond.
So I must repeat again that my client
will decide whether she will respond.
I ask the lawyer to have a serious
talk with Miss Salander.
This is, as I say, for her own sake.
Yes ...
I was surprised that she was
so small and slender as a girl.
- How did Lisbeth Salander do?
- Well under the circumstances.
- What about the allegations?
- No comments.
You are defending her
and have to say something.
Here is Lisbeth's autobiography.
- When did she write it?
- Does anybody care?
She's expected to participate in hearings.
- So, physically, she has recovered.
- But not mentally?
It's known that Lisbeth Salander, for several
years, has been treated in mental hospitals.
You mean Lisbeth Salander
still is mentally ill?
I cannot make that diagnosis.
I've sought a psychiatric
examination to get answers.
It's made by Dr Peter Teleborian
at St. Stephen's Hospital in Uppsala.
Peter Teleborian ...
What a surprise.
Is there a risk that the
trial will be postponed?
No, the police investigation progresses
as well as the proceedings.
ERIKA. IS IT YOUR STYLE: OR DID YOU BUY SOME-
THING FOR GREGER? HE'LL BE HOME ON SATURDAY. AFRAID, ERIKA? YOU SHOULD BE.
Christer?
- Is it from the same sender?
- Yes.
"It'll get worse now.
Everything's complete"
Is it us?
- Micke traced the sender?
- He called somebody.
It hasn't helped.
We might call and report it.
- We can't just wait until it happens
- I want to talk to Mikael first.
- I'll call them.
- No. I'm the publisher.
It is I who has received the email.
I don't go behind Mikaels' back.
We must stick together.
And agree. Especially now.
I'll call Mickael.
Hello, Lisbeth.
You should know that I'm sorry that
you've ended up in this situation.
I'll try to help you in
every possible way I can.
I hope we can work
together, you and me.
I thought we got to know
each other pretty well.
At the time.
You were stubborn-
And unusually difficult to treat
at twelve years old.
You bit my finger once.
Do you remember that?
You never understood that contact
can be a part of the treatment-
- That creates closeness and trust.
This applies especially to children.
Do you realize that I'm the person-
- With the greatest opportunity
to help you?
Do you?
- Hello. Are you still here?
- I called several times.
I was writing and had turned it off.
Same sender.
Chriser tried to call the police
today. But I stopped him.
We must solve this now, Mickael.
You and I run the newspaper.
We have a responsibility to our employees.
This is not just the two of us anymore.
I've had contact with one of Lisbeth's
hacker friends, Plague.
So we don't need the police?
If anyone can find the sender
it is him, but it takes some time.
It's faster than the police.
Are we talking days? Or weeks?
Honestly, I don't know.
Mrs. Giannini, I believe that your
Client should avoid trial.
This so-called autobiography-
- Containing unsubstantiated
and senseless accusations-
- against Peter Teleborian
and sollicitor Bjurman.
I know the contents.
But doesn't it prove that Lisbeth
Salander is in need of care?
No.
- For there is an option.
- What?
That what's written there is true
and that the people choose to believe it.
If we assume that Millennium
has something to publish-
- What can they have?
Worst case scenario:
A copy of Björcks' investigation.
They may not know
anything about us.
But he has great credibility.
And so does the magazine.
We could reduce
that credibility in some way?
Do what you want...
We have to put an end to this,
once and for all.
She phoned at quarter past
three in the night.
She had locked herself
in a room upstairs.
- We were there 20 minutes later.
- Do you have any leads?
The police should investigate.
We're installing alarms in the house now.
Erika told me about the email threats.
They're probably linked
with what happened last night.
My contact's trying to trace them.
I don't want to involve the police.
It's time now. It's about direct
physical threats against you and Erika.
- Against me?
- Yes, against you as well.
Your silent alarm in the apartment
went off last night.
He was in there 17 minutes.
When we searched the apartment-
- We found 180 grams of cocaine
hidden in one of your speakers-
- And 120,000 Kroner in cash
in your closet.
- What the hell?
- They're trying to discredit you-
As they can't discredit the magazine.
- Is it still there?
- The money's still there.
The other has been removed.
- I'll have to call Erika.
- I think she's asleep.
- Erika.
- Hey. It's me.
I know what's happened.
- I want us to talk. Can I come over?
- No, you shouldn't come here.
We'll talk it over later.
- I want to see you now.
- I have to sleep for a few hours.
Three o'clock?
Samirs Gryta?
- Will you or won't you come?
- At three o'clock. I'll be there.
- Good. Bye.
- Bye.
- Hi. Do you know where Erika is?
- No.
She doesn't answer when I call.
Today's the deadline for the printer.
- I'm going to get in touch with her.
- Good. You have a visitor up there.
Do you understand what I'm saying?
Teleborian has written an opinion
to which I'm unable to respond.
The court will believe that.
If you read it, you'll realize I'm right.
He has fabricated it
together with the Section.
- If we can prove it ...
- How could that be?
No. I must postpone the trial and convince
Lisbeth to undergo another evaluation.
But she won't help.
No.
I'm seriously considering
giving up.
Samirs Gryta. You know it?
At three in the afternoon.
So I'll send these pages
to the printer.
Haven't you heard from Erica?
I talked to her. She was feeling
bad last night and wanted to sleep today.
- How is she now?
- Better. Damn, I gotta go.
Has she received more threatening emails?
We've really done excellent work
with this issue together.
- Shall we all have a beer later?
- No, I have a meeting at Samir.
There's an uncertainty
about how many people-
- Are linked to the Section's activities.
In addition, There may be several more
people we don't know yet.
The key people we've already identified,
and they'll be arrested in a major joint action.
I'll give more information about this later.
It's ten minutes to three. We'll pause,
and gather here again in an hour.
- Has there been any developments today?
- Clinton's been receiving dialysis.
The others have come and gone.
Jonas Sandberg is probably the
only one being social.
10:30, he met with two
people at a pizzeria in Bredäng.
- Who did he meet?
- That's new faces to me.
- They look Eastern European...
- The Nikolic brothers
Tomi and Miro Nikolic. From Serbia,
but they've lived in Huddinge.
Very unpleasant types.
Sharpshooters in the Civil War.
Miro's wanted for aggravated assault
but they live mostly in Serbia, so...
Mikael. Wait.
Hey, Samir.
Sorry I'm late.
- How are you?
- How do you think?
- Why didn't you call me last night?
- What could you have done?
I called Milton Security
because I needed help.
We have to look after our people, Micke.
Samir Gryta on Söder.
Connect me quickly, please.
I stopped the magazine.
I called the printer.
This also applies to Malin and Christer.
Their safety.
- Did you call the print shop?
- I won't take responsibility for this.
- It's too dangerous.
- Shit...
- Micke, telephone for you.
- No, not now.
It's very important.
Sorry.
- They're shooting!
- We'll take a shortcut.
Down!
Police! Police! Show your hands!
Police! Show your hands!
How is it?
Are you okay?
- Here, something to wipe your head.
- How are you?
Get out with Blomkvist and Berger
as fast as hell.
We'll go out through the kitchen.
The kitchen!
Two police officers were
eating at the restaurant-
- And recognized the two brothers. One
was wanted for aggravated assault.
An exchange of fire broke out as they
were arrested, but no one was hurt.
The two brothers are now charged
with attempted murder.
That went well.
Shit!
Bad idea from the beginning.
No, but I didn't know
that one of them was wanted.
It's my fault.
- What will the Nikolic brothers tell?
- Not that they had a contract for the killing.
They're not that fucking stupid.
I talked to Christer and Malin.
- They can't stay at the office now.
- No ...
I think about Dag and Mia.
We could've also died today.
Both of us.
There's no job that's
worth dying for.
No ...
We don't know if they just thought of
killing you, Mikael, or Erika as well.
But the idea was that the police
would find the drugs and money-
And link it with a
Yugoslavian drug deal.
- What of the other staff editors?
- We will close for a couple of days.
We'll postpone the release of
the magazine, also.
I suggest that you and Erika
have bodyguards.
No, I don't want somebody following me.
- Now we'll see how it goes.
- Have you had contact with her?
What happened?
I'll push for Lisbeth Salander to be
committed to the mental hospital-
- Failing that, a long prison sentence.
Usually that tends to be reversed.
Yes, but in this case-
- The psychiatric opinion is
so unequivocal-
- I don't have any alternative.
Thank you very much.
The trial of Lisbeth Salander begins
here in Stockholms' District Court-
- Today at 13, in about an hour.
It's expected to last three days
and has aroused great public interest.
Both the police and the prosecutor
have prepared their case-
- and given information to the media
while the defense has denied...
Holy shit.
Is it time?
- I didn't sleep one hour last night.
- It'll go well.
Yeah ...!
It will go well.
- So.
- Thanks. See you later. Bye.
Back, back!
I can only regret-
- That Lisbeth Salander didn't say
a single word during seven hearings.
But the fact doesn't weaken
any of the charges against her.
Thanks.
So I leave the floor to the lawyer.
From the defense side,
we reject all counts.
We will prove that the
prosecutor's allegations are false-
- And that my client has been exposed
to serious gross legal violations.
I'll ask that my client
be declared innocent-
- That her guardianship be repealed
and that she be released immediately.
Thanks.
Does the prosecutor have anything to add?
I'd like to request that negotiations
be conducted behind closed doors.
It's about a vulnerable person, her
psychological health and wellbeing-
- As well as about material which
is marked confidential-
- And in some parts may pertain
to national security.
See you tonight.
Great.
So we shall begin by
trying to get some clarity in-
- Why you went to Gosseberga-
- To try to kill your father
Alexander Zalachenko-
- Also known as Karl Axel Bodin.
Should we understand from your silence
that you don't want to answer questions?
I'll gladly answer questions.
Then maybe you can answer the question.
I haven't heard any questions yet.
I asked if you went to Gosseberga
with the intention to kill your father.
No, you said you wanted to
try to clarify-
- why I drove to Gosseberga to try to
kill my father, Alexander Zalachenko.
It was an allegation where you anticipated
a response, an unverified assertion.
- Answer the question.
- No.
- No, what?
- No is my answer to the question.
Did you bury an axe in the head of your father?
Yes.
He was seriously wounded, and I argue
that it is attempted murder.
What's your opinion?
That was two assertions.
Which should I state my opinion on?
If the axe blow to the head of
your father was attempted murder?
There was no attempted murder.
It was self-defense.
Thanks.
Let me know if you need anything.
- Can you get cigarettes?
- Forget it.
Thanks.
- Hi.
- How does it feel to have bodyguards?
- It's okay...
As long as they stay outside.
Erika ...
I couldn't do it.
You are an egoist.
And stupid.
I'm staying home this week.
Next week also.
I have to be sure that I
make the right decision.
Yes.
Is it about us or Millennium?
Both.
I think.
I'll be in touch.
Take care.
Damn.
Salander, it's time.
Lisbeth Salanders'
so-called autobiography,
- Lacks any credibility.
It's a series of allegations
about various individuals-
- Each one more absurd than the other.
Overall, it's an expression of-
- The paranoid-schizophrenia that
Lisbeth Salander is suffering from.
Can you give an example?
The most obvious,
the depiction of the rape-
- She claims-
- Her guardian, lawyer
Bjurman, is guilty of.
The entire narrative
with all its details-
- Is a classic example
on the kind of grotesque fantasy-
- That children tend to exhibit.
Now, Lisbeth Salander is no child,
she's a grown woman.
That is correct. Although it remains
to be seen-
- exactly what her mental level
may be.
In principle you're right.
But she, like a child,-
- Is unable to distinguish fantasy
from Reality.
I understand.
In 1993, Lisbeth Salander was forcibly
hospitalized at St. Stephen's.
Over the years that she lived there,
you had responsibility for her.
Is that correct?
- Yes.
How many days was she
kept in restraints there?
I mean fastened in bed with straps.
That, I can't possibly remember.
But not many.
Approximately?
Possibly ... thirty. But I fail to
understand what relevance this has.
Lisbeth Salander herself, claims
it was 381 days in total.
That's pure fantasy.
Absurd.
She wasn't strapped down
with belts for more than a year...
- ... Of the two years she lived there?
- Of course not.
The defense repeatedly tried to get
Lisbeth Salander's medical records-
- From the years she was hospitalized
at St. Stephen's, but without success.
- Can you explain why?
- Yes, it's confidential.
- It always is in such
investigations, as a rule.
The lawyer should know.
I have a copy here of Lisbeth
Salander's records from the two years-
- 1993 and 1994.
Here it's clear that Lisbeth Salander
was restrained by straps for 381 days.
Attorney Giannini, how's this
revelant to the trial?
I want to demonstrate that Peter Teleborian
isn't telling the truth in this situation.
Attorney Giannini, the records of
'93 and '94 can't be used today-
- To question Peter Teleborians' credibility.
I felt like an idiot.
It wasn't wrong;
for Teleborian is a fucking liar.
This is proven in Björcks' investigation.
It proves what he did then,
not what he does now.
When the prosecutor submitted Teleborians'
new opinion, I did nothing.
She'll land in the madhouse again
and I can't do anything about it.
Who are you?
Plague.
What is this?
Peter Teleborians private computer.
Copied on a USB key.
Sorry. Come in.
What's it contain?
Everything you need.
Plus some nasty shit.
Annika, I have everything you need here.
Cooperation with the Section.
Several versions of the psychiatric report, falsified dates-
- eMail correspondence, everything.
- There you are. Yes, it was good.
- Here.
- The reports I never saw.
Read it over lunch.
The dates are important.
Great, great.
See you later. Bye Bye.
You ended up at St. Stephen's
- After having poured petrol over
your dad and then lighting the fire.
- Yes.
- Why did you do it?
Because he beat up my mother
for several years.
On the 12th of June, 1993, he assaulted her
so brutally that she was handicapped.
- She received permanent brain damage.
- Did you tell that to anyone?
- Yes, the police officers
who interrogated me-
- To the social worker, different doctors,
a priest, and that pig.
Why do you call Peter
Teleborian a pig?
When I came to St. Stephen's
I tried to explain what had happened.-
- But he claimed that I fantasized.
As punishment, I was put in straps.
That's pure nonsense.
Again an exemple-
- That your client has no ability
to differentiate fantasy from reality.
- You lie, you fucking pig.
- Here we speak appropriately in the court.
Now I would like to move on
with the sexual abuse-
- As a lawyer, Nils Bjurman
exploited my client.
That's not the case.
These are absurd allegations,
without a shred of evidence.
It's an example of the legal
abuse Lisbeth suffered.
When it comes to Frederick Clinton
he may be on dialysis.-
- In the care of
Karolinska Hospital.
Everyone here will get all the files
with all the necessary information.
I repeat.
Group 1: Bublanski.
Group 2: Svensson.
Group 3: Modig.
Group 4: Figuerola.
Group 5: Holmberg.
For questions or queries speak to
your respective chief operating officer.
Good luck.
We're here at the ongoing trial
of Lisbeth Salander-
- Who, according to Millennium was
subjected to a series of legal assaults-
- Orchestrated by a secret organization
known as "The Section".
This is the third day of the trial.
- You maintain that Bjurman raped you?
- Yes.
- When, in that case, would it have happened?
- Not "in this case"
It was Tuesday the 18th of February, 2008 -
And Friday the 7th of March, same year.
It's clear in my biography.
- Did you notify the police?
- No.
- Why not?
- The police have never listened to me.
- Did you seek medical attention for your injuries?
No.
- Did you talk to somebody about it?
- No.
The late lawyer, Nils Bjurman, has never
been convicted of any criminal offense.
He's never been reported or been
under investigation for anything.
However, it's my duty
to point out that Lisbeth Salander-
- Is diagnosed
as paranoid schizophrenic.
She has spent several years
at a child psychiatric clinic-
- And has been under guardianship
since she was eighteen years old.
How regrettable it is, that-
- Lisbeth Salander has a totally
confused view of the world.
It appears with abundant
clarity in this "autobiography".
Nowhere else does the rupture
of her sense of realism appear so clearly.
In light of the lack of evidence-
- We will try to evaluate the credibility
of her claims in her words and statements.
- Is the prosecutor finished?
- Yes.
- Then the lawyer can present evidence.
Peter Teleborian claims
that Lisbeth Salander is lying-
- On the allegations that she was
sexually exploited by lawyer Bjurman.
The Prosecutor is of the same opinion.
- I shall now demonstrate what
Lisbeth claims is completely true.
- When was this filmed, Lisbeth?
On the 7th of March, 2008.
I used a hidden camera.
If you're good...
If you ...
I'll be good to you.
Are you good?
Are you good? Are you good?
It's too late.
Stop the film!
Enough!
- Why did you record it?
- Bjurman had raped me before.
- He'd forced me to perform oral sex.
He demanded more if I wanted to
get access to my money.
It was the only way
to obtain evidence against him.
The only way to get him to stop.
We'll take a break.
We need 20 minutes.
Can we take an hour?
We need to collect ourselves after this.
Then it'll be a one hour break.
- Sorry I'm late.
- It's okay. Thank you.
You're submitting new material?
It's the same the Court already has,
but with small, crucial differences.
I'll get to it.
- Then I give the floor to the lawyer.
- Thank you.
Yes ...
No one can deny that Lisbeth
was subjected to-
- serious sexual abuse by her
guardian, lawyer Nils Bjurman.
A person she thought
she could trust.
As I've said, this illustrates the
type of prolonged assaults against Lisbeth.
The attacks have both been
psychological and legal.
The person who has a major responsibility
for this is Dr. Peter Teleborian.
He was, in 1993, together
with Gunnar Björck-
- a member of an illegal
group within the Security Police-
- And he wrote a forensic
psychiatric report-
- With the intent to imprison
a dangerous witness-
- Thus, Lisbeth Salander, was transferred
to a secure psychiatric clinic.
There must be some moderation
on these accusations ...
Excuse me, but I was speaking.
This occurred after Lisbeth had poured
gasoline on her father-
- Alexander Zalachenko, in a
desperate attempt to save the mother.
But those who protected Zalachenko-
- Made sure to put a lid on it
and classified the matter.
- Instead, with Peter Teleborians' help-
- Lisbeth was locked away
at St Stephen's in Uppsala.
It's a crazy accusation!
- I've tried to help Lisbeth
Salander in the best way. She tried...
- Yesterday, Peter Teleborian presented
his new legal psychiatric opinion here.
Once again, it proposes-
- The compulsory detention of Lisbeth
Salander and locking her up.
But just like in 1993,
it's under false pretenses.
That is quite...
I must ask you to allow the lawyer to
finish speaking. Thank you.
Thanks.
The statement is based on
"observations" of my client.
These must have been from the time
She was moved to Kronoberg-
- on October 6, and must have been
completed by November 5.
Is that correct, Peter Teleborian?
Yes. I ask the court
to remember these dates.
You asked for permission to visit my
client in the hospital, but it was denied.
Is it true?
I wish to call two witnesses.
No!
Police, drop the gun!
Lie still!
Yes ... Do you recognize this document?
Yes.
It's the psychiatric report on
Lisbeth Salander, by Peter Teleborian.
There are currently three versions.
The first, dated September 20th;
the second on October 1st.
And this is the third,
which is dated October 6th.
You gave me the documents.
And I've noticed that the first
statement from October
- Is identical to the statement
Peter Teleborian preferred yesterday.
Dated November 5th.
That is, to say the least, remarkable.
My conclusion is that Peter Teleborian
wrote his report and diagnosis-
- Before he met with Lisbeth Salander.
Thus, it lacks all credibility.
Inspector Edklinth, is it correct-
- That you had these statements about
Salander given to you by Mikael Blomkvist?
Yes.
- What's your conclusion?
- That they're false.
They were written long before-
- Peter Teleborian had the opportunity to
meet Lisbeth Salander in custody.
They where forged in collaboration
with a certain Jonas Sandberg.
That's a lie.
- Is it a lie?
- No, not at all.
The documents are dated
and there's email correspondence-
- Between Peter Teleborian and
Jonas Sandberg proving this.
He's part of an illegal group within
the Security Police since the 1970s-
- Which protected
Alexander Zalachenko.
The group was behind the decision-
- To incarcerate Lisbeth Salander
at St. Stephen's Hospital in 1993.
Jonas Sandberg is
one of a dozen or so-
- Who where arrested today.
He's suspected of involvement in
the murder of Gunnar Björck.
Possibly another murder.
We have evidence and multiple confessions.
Would Peter Teleborian care to
comment on this?
Two police officers are waiting
outside the courtroom.
They're to take Peter Teleborian
with them for questioning.
Why?
He's under arrest on suspicion of violating
the law on serious child pornography charges.
Specifically, for the possession of 8,000
child pornography images and movies-
- Found on his computer.
This has been seized.
Please come with me?
Please be seated.
The court was unable to assess
all the new information from the last hour-
- But finds no reason to keep
Lisbeth Salander in custody.
So you're free pending
the court's verdic.
Yes ...
That's right, I have keys
from Micke to give to you.
Are you sure you don't want
to join Millennium?
You can drop me off
at Folkungatan.
You know that this is all
thanks to Micke, right?
Yes. But ...
Yes.
I don't know where you live?
No, not now. Maybe later.
What will you do now?
- I must be able to reach you.
- You can contact me by email.
Good.
Bye.
- Why did it finish like this?
- Justice prevailed.
- So now there's a party?
- Now there's a party.
- What's going to happen now?
- Now it begins!
suspected of murder, among other things.
The organization operated
from this building in Stockholm-
- and is responsible for serious gross
abuses against Lisbeth Salander.
But the story begins in the 60s.
When "The Section" was created to
guard and monitor the nation's interests.
Officially, they never existed.
Evidence suggests that not even
the State Police knew about the group.
In the mid-70s "The Section" recruited
a top Soviet spy ...
Lisbeth is released
pending the verdict.
Then she'll either be acquitted
or get probation.
- Here.
- What's this?
It's the legacy of Zalachenko.
I don't want anything
from that pig.
No, but you are of legal age now.
So I need your signature
that you've received this.
There are securities totalling 300,000 -
Plus a property in Gosseberga,
valued at 1.5 million.
I don't want anything to do with it.
Then there is this ...
A derelict brickworks at a
place outside Norrtälje.
Just the plot is valued at 150,000.
All right.
Sell the dump and give the money to
charity.
I think you need to read it through.
Then I can sell it for you.
Micke says hello.
- Pizza Bussola? There you go.
- Thanks. Bye.
Damn!
You deserve to die,
you fucking freak.
- 118118
- Yes, hello.
Give me the number for the
motorcycle club in Svavelsjö.
- Who is this?
- Are you interested in Niedermann?
I'm listening.
SOS Alarm.
Police killer Ronald Niedermann is
at Skederyds brickyard at Norrtälje.
A biker gang went to kill him.
They're heavily armed.
- Am I disturbing you?
- I was in the bath.
- Yes, I see...
- Have you seen the news?
- No.
Ronald Niedermann is dead. A gang
from Svavelsjö MC killed him.
Your old friend was shot by Sonny.
Now the police have him.
Thank you for everything.
Thanks.
Thank you.
See ya.
- We'll talk.
- Absolutely.