<sect1 id="gpsd.c"><title><filename>gpsd.c</filename></title>
<informaltable frame='all' pgwide='1'>
<tgroup cols='2'>
<colspec colname='c1'></colspec>
<colspec colname='c2'></colspec>
<spanspec spanname='s1' namest='c1' nameend='c2'></spanspec>

<!-- Not documented: json_devicelist_dump(), rstrip() -->

<thead>
<row>
  <entry>Functions:-</entry><entry>This is the main body of the daemon.</entry>
</row>
</thead>

<tfoot>
<row>
  <entry spanname='s1' align='left'>Notes based on code as of Mon Apr 5 21:38:06 2010 -0400.</entry>
</row>
</tfoot>

<tbody>
<row>
  <entry><function>static void onsig(int sig)</function></entry>
  <entry><para>This is a simple catchall routine to trap wanted
  signal. Simply store the signal number in a variable to advise the
  main loop which signal to handle.</para></entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><function>static int daemonize(void)</function></entry>
  <entry><para>Try to <function>fork()</function> a child process. The
  parent will get a return value of either -1 (on a failure to
  <function>fork()</function>) or non-zero (the child's PID). The
  parent routine will use this information to either return -1 or exit
  with an exit code of 0 (i.e. the parent terminates, leaving the
  child running).</para><para>The child instance gets a return value
  of 0 (on an unsuccessful <function>fork()</function> there is no
  child), so this value is used as the trigger to do the following
  useful stuff.</para><para>First, the child tries to create a new
  session, returning -1 if unable to do so. If succesful, it will have
  inherited the exiting parent's session.</para><para>Next switch to
  the root directory and try to open <quote>/dev/null</quote>. If that
  succeeds, force stdin, stdout and stderr to duplicate the fd of
  <quote>/dev/null</quote>. If the fd being used for the operation is
  >2, release it.</para><para>Finally, set the flag which indicates
  the process is in the background and return a value of
  0.</para></entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><function>void gpsd_report(int errlevel, const char *fmt, ... )</function></entry>
  <entry><para>This code is used for error reporting, but is dependant
  on SQUELCH_DISABLE so that embedded systems (for example) are not
  burdened with unnecessary noise. The first thing to check is if the
  error level offered is high enough to be of interest (controlled by
  the debug level we are running at).</para><para>If we are
  interested, the first step is to protect the code with a mutex if we
  are using the 1PPS input.</para><para>Now we build a message buffer
  which has a fixed header (<quote>gpsd: </quote>) and the incoming
  data. The output buffer is prepared (load the start with a NULL) and
  then the input buffer is scanned, byte-by-byte, up to its
  terminating NULL. The scanned data is transferred on the fly to the
  output buffer subject to the following tests:-</para><para>If the
  character is printable, it passes through unchanged.</para><para>If
  it is a space and either of the next two bytes is NULL it will also
  pass through unchanged.</para><para>In any other case, it is copied
  across as a hexadecimal string like
  <quote>x09</quote>.</para><para>The completed output buffer is then
  either sent to the system logger if we are in background mode
  (daemon) or to the stderr file if we are in foreground
  mode.</para></entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><function>static void usage(void)</function></entry>
  <entry><para>Simply print a big list of the invocation parameters to
  the default <application>gpsd</application> port (2947, allocated by
  IANA).</para></entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><function>static int passivesock_af(char *service, char *tcp_or_udp, int qlen)</function></entry>
  <entry><para>Initialise an Internet socket address structure and
  preload the family and address fields to accept Internet Protocol
  and any address.</para><para>Test to see if the incoming service and
  protocol exist in <function>/etc/services</function>. If they do,
  store the port number in the structure (massaging byte order as
  needed); if they don't, exit with a -1.</para><para>Test to see if
  the protocol is listed in <function>/etc/services</function>,
  exiting with -1 if it is not.</para><para>Test if the protocol is
  udp or not, setting the type accordingly.</para><para>Try to open a
  socket with the accumulated settings, exiting with -1 if it
  fails.</para><para>Try to set the socket options correctly, again
  exiting with -1 if it fails.</para><para>Try to bind to the open
  socket; if it fails exit with -1 as earlier, but give a special
  warning if the error indicates that <application>gpsd</application>
  may already be active on the socket.</para><para>If we are using a
  stream type socket and we are unable to listen to the port we exit
  with -1.</para><para>The last possibility is a successful set of
  operations which is signalled by returning the socket fd
  number.</para></entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><function>static int passivesocks(char *service, char *tcp_or_udp, int qlen, int socks[])</function></entry>
  <entry><para>Open a passive socket for each supported address
  family; presently the supported families are IPV4 and IPv6. This
  socket will be used to listen for client command
  connections. Sockets are left in the final array argument, and the
  number successfully opened is returned.</para>></entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><function>static int filesock(char *filename)</function></entry>
  <entry><para>Try and open a socket for Local (UNIX) communications
  in streaming mode. If the open fails, return with a
  -1.</para><para>If it opens, copy the incoming filename into the
  socket control structure, bind to the socket and try to listen on
  it.</para><para>Signal a failure by returning -1 and success by
  returning the socket fd number.</para></entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><function>static void adjust_max_fd(int fd, bool on)</function></entry>
  <entry><para>If the incoming boolean flag is active, check if the fd
  number passed is greater than the highest seen so far. If so, save
  it as the new highest value.</para><para>If the boolean is passive
  we can take some further action, depending if we are interested in
  limiting the maximum number of devices and client fds (set by
  compile time options).</para><para>If we are not limiting ourselves,
  then we check for the case when we are actually at the highest fd
  seen so far. In that case, scan through all fds available to the
  system and store the highest active fd number in our allocation set
  as the new highest value.</para></entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><function>static struct subscriber_t* allocate_client(void)</function></entry>
  <entry><para>Scan through all the client file descriptors, looking
  for one which does not have a device allocated to it.</para><para>On
  a match, exit early, returning this fd.</para><para>If none are
  available, return a NULL.</para></entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><function>static void detach_client(struct subscriber_t *sub)</function></entry>
  <entry><para>Close the given fd and remove it from our allocation set.</para><para>Make a call to <function>adjust_max_fd()</function> to housekeep the highest fd marker if needed.</para><para>Set important fields in the client's datablock to safe values for the next re-use, then return.</para></entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><function>static ssize_t throttled_write(struct subscriber_t *sub, char *buf, ssize_t len)</function></entry>
  <entry><para>Check if we have a high enough debug level active to warrant printing out the information we are about to send to the client.</para><para>Make the actual <function>write()</function> call and if that was successful, return the counter value from that operation.</para><para>If we have suffered some kind of failure, try to analyse it.</para><para>On a short write, detach the client and return a 0.</para><para>Trap <function>EAGAIN</function> or <function>EINTR</function> and return a 0.</para><para>Trap <function>EBADF</function> or a <function>EWOULDBLOCK</function> where the client has not read data for more than a reasonable amount of time and generate a suitable report.</para><para>For all other errors, generate a general error. In these last several cases, call <function>detach_cient()</function>.</para><para>Finally, return the status (-1 in this case).</para></entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><function>static void notify_watchers(struct gps_device_t *device, const char *sentence, ...)</function></entry>
  <entry><para>For every possible subscriber, check if the subscriber is in watcher mode and is interested in the gps device indicated in the calling parameter <function>gps_device_t</function>.</para><para>If so, send the data via a call to <function>throttled_write()</function>.</para></entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><function>static struct gps_device_t *find_device(const char *device_name)</function></entry>
  <entry><para>For every possible channel, check if the channel is allocated and if the device on the channel is the one passed to us.</para><para>If it is so, exit early and return the channel number.</para><para>If there is no match, return a NULL.</para></entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><function>static void deactivate_device(struct gps_device_t *device)</function></entry>
  <entry><para>Deactivate device, but leave it in the device pool; do
  not free it.  This means it will be available to be watched on
  subsequent client opens.</para></entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><function>bool open_device(struct gps_device_t *devp)</function></entry>
  <entry><para>Try to activate the device via a call to
  <function>gpsd_activate()</function>.</para><para>If this fails
  return <quote>false</quote>.</para><para>If it succeeds, add the
  fd to our list of active fds, housekeep the highest fd number
  and return <quote>true</quote>.</para></entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><function>static bool add_device(const char *device_name)</function></entry>
  <entry><para>Add a device to the pool of those available. If in
  nowait mode, open it immediately; otherwise initialize it and make
  it available for future watches, but don't open it yet.</para></entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><function>static bool awaken(struct subscriber_t *user, struct gps_device_t *device)</function></entry>

  <entry><para>If the device is not initialized, attempt to open the
  specified device on behalf of the specified user. If you succeed
  and the device has an active fd, you're done. If it does not, make a call to
  <function>gpsd_activate()</function>.</para><para>If this fails,
  return <quote>false</quote>, if not, add the fd to our list of
  active fds and housekeep the highest fd.</para><para>Check if the
  user is in watcher mode but not tied to a specific
  device.</para></entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><function>static char *snarfline(char *p, char **out)</function></entry>
  <entry><para>Copy the input line into a new buffer stopping at the
  first non-printable or whitespace character.</para></entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><function>static bool privileged_user(struct gps_device_t *device)</function></entry>
  <entry><para>Scan all subscribers and count all who are connected to
  the device. If only the one user is connected, return
  <quote>true</quote>, otherwise return
  <quote>false</quote>.</para></entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><function>static void handle_request(struct subscriber_t* sub, char *buf, const char **after, char *reply, size_t replylen)</function></entry>
  <entry><para>Perform a single GPSD JSON command. Accept the command
  response into a reply buffer, and update the after pointer to point
  just after the parsed JSON object.</para></entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><function>static int handle_gpsd_request(struct subscriber_t *sub, const char *buf)
</function></entry>
  <entry><para>Parse multiple GPSD JSON commands out of a buffer and
  perform each. Ship all responses back to the user via
  <function>throttled_write()</function>.</para></entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><function>static void handle_control(int sfd, char *buf)</function></entry>
  <entry><para>This code is similar in function to
  <function>handle_gpsd_request()</function> in that it parses user
  input. It expects the commands to be one per line and despatches
  them according to the leading character, which is limited to one of
  '-', '+' or '!'.</para><para>In the first case, the body of the
  command is assumed to be a device to remove from the search list. If
  found, it is removed, any clients are advised and <quote>OK</quote>
  is written to the calling socket fd. If the device is not found
  <quote>ERROR</quote> is written to the calling socket
  fd.</para><para>In the second case, the body of the command is
  assumed to be a device to be used by the daemon. If the device is
  already known, or does not respond to
  <function>open_device()</function>, <quote>ERROR</quote> is written
  to the calling socket fd, otherwise <quote>OK</quote> is
  written.</para><para>In the third case, the command is assumed to be
  a device-specific control string in the form
  <quote>!device_name=control_string</quote>. If the string is
  ill-formed or the device is not found <quote>ERROR</quote> is
  written to the calling socket fd. If all is well, the control string
  is written to the device and <quote>OK</quote> is written to the
  calling socket fd.</para></entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><function>int main(int argc, char *argv[])</function></entry>
  <entry><para>If the 1PPS function is compiled in, initialise the
  local mutex structure for use by the program.</para><para>A
  <function>while()</function> loop reads in any command line
  arguments which are options and handles the options. Most set an
  internal variable to control action when running, either to a fixed
  value or to the associated option's parameter.</para><para>Carry out
  a series of calls to routines to set things up ready for the main
  task (e.g. opening a control socket if one is needed). We also take
  care of tasks such as daemonizing when appropriate. The last piece
  of preparation is to set the permissions of the default devices
  correctly if we are daemonizing and are presently running as
  root.</para><para>Switch to the compiled in user name (typically
  <quote>nobody</quote>) and the group used by the tty
  devices.</para><para>Now we clear important data for all the records
  in the subscriber list.</para><para>Use
  <function>setjmp()</function> to prepare things for when the daemon
  terminates.</para><para>Clear the semaphore variable which will
  contain the signal number if one arrives and set some important
  signals so they are trapped by the stub handler in
  <function>onsig()</function>.</para><para>Add the command and RTCM
  sockets (if active) to the list of active fds, housekeeping the
  highest fd number and pre-clear the list of control
  fds.</para><para>Process the remaining parameter on the command line
  which should be the device name and try to open the specified
  device.</para><para>Enter the main execution loop, a
  <function>while()</function> loop which terminates if a signal sets
  the semaphore variable. What follows will repeat over and over until
  an external termination happens.</para><para>First we make a working
  copy of the active fds and then we make a time-limited (1 second
  time limit) call to <function>select()</function> using the working
  copy of the fds. This means that when the
  <function>select()</function> returns, we will either have returned
  on timeout or because some fd became ready to
  read.</para><para>First we check if any new clients have come active
  and (if we have resources) allocate a subscriber slot to it, doing
  housekeeping such as adding it to the main list of active fds and
  removing it from the local copy of the list. If RTCM support is
  compiled in, the last operation is repeated for any new RTCM
  client. The operation is then repeated for any new control socket
  clients.</para><para>If we are expecting DGPS reports, make a call
  to <function>netgnss_poll()</function> and if there are no ready
  reports, clear the fd from the main and local active fd
  lists.</para><para>Check if any of the active control sockets has
  sent one or more commands.</para><para>For every one which has sent
  commands, make calls to <function>handle_control()</function> to
  process them and remove the associated fd from the main and control
  lists of active fds.</para><para>Poll every active gps device and
  send RTCM data to it (if needed), followed by reading its output (if
  any). If the device returns an error, disable the device. If it has
  gone off-line, disable the device.</para><para>If we get here, we
  have something to handle, so we take care of a device which we know
  about, but do not have a subtype for.</para><para>We send the
  available data to all subscribers who are connected to this
  device. If the data is RTCM information, pass it to all GPS devices
  that can accept the data.</para><para>Handle any subscribers who are
  in watcher mode building up an appropriate set of requests, depending
  on the available data and passing the requests to
  <function>handle_gpsd_request()</function>.</para><para>If we care
  about DBUS, send the fix to the DBUS.</para><para><emphasis>Note
  that this small section of code is presently disabled pending
  development of the DGNSS function.</emphasis> If DGNSS is available
  and we have a fix, we poll a DGNSS report via
  <function>dgnss_autoconnect()</function>.</para><para>Loop round all
  clients and process active ones. We check for input from them and if
  the read fails, the client is released with
  <function>detach_client()</function>. If it succeeds, any data is
  handled via <function>handle_rtc_request()</function> or
  <function>handle_gpsd_request()</function>.</para><para>If the
  transaction fails, the client is released with
  <function>detach_client()</function>.</para><para>If the client has
  timed out with no device assigned, it is released with
  <function>detach_client()</function>.</para><para>If the client has
  a device, but has timed out on no response (when not in raw or
  watcher modes) it is released with
  <function>detach_client()</function>.</para><para>If we are not
  running in <quote>nowait</quote> mode, we are supposed to go idle
  after a timeout when there are no clients.</para><para>If a device
  (with a known type) has no active clients, then we can actually make
  it idle via <function>gpsd_deactivate()</function>.</para><para>If
  we reach here, we are out of the endless while loop. We check if the
  signal was <function>SIGHUP</function> and restart the program if it
  was. If it is any other signal, we deallocate all channels and wrap
  up any devices. Finally we check for the existence of a control
  socket or a pid file and delete them.</para></entry>
</row>
</tbody>

</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect1>
